Jean Nordhaus literary papers, 1975-2013 MS2328
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Jean Nordhaus literary papers
1975-2013
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2328
1.75 Linear Feet
This collection contains the personal files of Jean Nordhaus and the organizational files for the Capitol Hill Poetry Group. The Capitol Hill Poetry Group is a critique group that was co-founded by Nordhaus along with Shirley Cochrane in Washington, DC in 1975. The collection covers the period of 1975-2013, and includes personal, administrative, event-related, and creative documents.
Biographical Note
Jean Nordhaus was born in Baltimore, Maryland and received a BA in Philosophy from Barnard College and a PhD in German Literature from Yale University. She moved to Washington in 1964 and became engaged with the DC poetry community in the early 70's, while teaching English at what was then Federal City College (today UDC.) She co-founded a critique group on the Hill, the Capitol Hill Poetry Group and started attending readings at the Library of Congress and the Folger Shakespeare Library. (Stanley Kunitz was Poetry Consultant to the Library of Congress at that time and lived during his tenure in a townhouse on 4th Street, SE.) In the late 70's Nordhaus became Dance Editor of The Washington Review of the Arts (Bernard Welt was the Poetry Editor) and soon after began writing dance reviews for the Washington Post.
From 1980-83, and again for a year during the 1991-92 season, she served as Poetry Coordinator at the Folger Shakespeare Library. During her tenure, the Folger started a second lunchtime poetry series called the Moveable Muse, with weekly readings at alternating downtown locations: the Renwick Gallery, the Phillips Collection, and other venues. She also published a monthly listing of poetry events and news called the Poetry Clearinghouse. While at the Folger, she organized a 2-day conference on the translation of poetry featuring George Steiner as the keynote speaker and coordinated the PEN Faulkner Award for Fiction during its first year in Washington.
Her first full-length collection, A Bracelet of Lies, was published by Washington Writers' Publishing House in 1987. She served as president of the cooperative press for 6 years, from 1988-94. In 2010, she became Review Editor for Poet Lore. Her other books include:
Innocence, (Ohio State University Press, November 2006), winner of the Charles B. Wheeler Award
The Porcelain Apes of Moses Mendelssohn, an extended biography in verse of the 18th century German-Jewish philosopher (Milkweed Editions, 2002)
A Purchase of Porcelain, Kinloch Rivers Chapbook Contest Winner, Published by the Poetry Society of South Carolina, 1998.
My Life in Hiding, (Quarterly Review of Literature, Volume XXX, 1991), winner of Colladay Prize.
A Language of Hands, (chapbook) SCOP Publications, 1982 ISBN 0-930526-05-8 $3.50, out of print, although I have a few copies.
In translation: The Porcelain Apes of Moses Mendelssohn, tr. Moshe Dor, Carmel Publications, Israel, 1996. Her work has been published in numerous journals, including Poetry, Ploughshares, American Poetry Review, and the New Republic; and in anthologies including Best American Poetry, the Pushcart Prize Anthology and The Other Side of the Hill I and II.
Beltway Poetry Quarterly, 5 poems, Volume 5:2, Spring 2004: http://washingtonart.com/beltway/nordhaus.html
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, poetry, teaching materials and other paper records. There are two distinct groups of documents: the personal files of Jean Nordhaus and the files of the critique group she co-founded, the Capitol Hill Poetry Group. Nordhaus' personal files include correspondence, drafts and final versions of Nordhaus', her friends, and the Capitol Hill Poetry Group members' poetry. The Capitol Hill Poetry Group's bank account information, book manuscript, book deal related documents, an autobiographical organizational history, photographs, and press clippings. In addition there is event information including invitations, programs, notes, exhibition catalogues, an audio recording (on cassette), and speaking preparation for workshops, conferences, readings, and literary festivals; research, interviews, and drafts of speeches and book introductions. The material dates from 1975 to 2013. Items in the collection cover Nordhaus' engagement in the literary scene, especially in Washington, DC's Capitol Hill Poetry Group, and reflect both administrative and creative aspects of her work.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jean Nordhaus, Accession June 3, 2014 (2014.07)
Arrangement
Organized into 2 series: Personal files, and Capital Hill Poetry Group files.
Poetry; Poetry -- Workshops; Poetry -- 20th century; Capitol Hill Poetry Group; Nordhaus, Jean
- Personal files, 1975-2013; series 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  The materials of this series from Jean Nordhaus' personal papers include event informational packets, invitations, and preparatory documents, as well as catalogues and programs; correspondence, drafts and final versions of written pieces, research, interview transcriptions, and notes. Materials cover Adrienne Rich, Mark Strand, Milne Holton, the controversy surrounding poetry by Jonathan Yardley through editorials in the Washington Post, several conferences, literary festivals and workshops including the 1976 AU conference, 2011 AWP conference, the 1984 and 1986 poetry conferences at St. Mary's College, the 1996 Creative Writing Festival for senior adults in Washington, DC, the St. Mary's College Literary festivals of 1980-1987 and 1994, and workshops like the 1997 In the Garden series.
  - Adrienne Rich, 1991-1993; series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Age/poetry conference, 1997; series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - AU conference, 1976; series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - AWP Feb 2011, series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1994; series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence 12/94-12/96, 1994-1996; series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence 2000-2003, series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence 2004-, 2004-2013; series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Creative writing festival, 1996 September 19; series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Emily Dickinson: Letter to the world An exhibition at the Folger Shakespeare Library, 1986 May - 1986, June; series 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Folger Broadside - Zadravac readings, 1992 February 03; series 2 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Folger poetry series info, 2010; series 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Holton interview, 1979 May; series 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - HoCoPoLitSo (Howard County Poetry and Literature Society) packet, 2003; series 2 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Innocence, experience LC reading, 2007 March; series 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - In the garden, 1997 September 21; series 2 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - KE2, 1996; series 2 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mt. Vernon, 1990 September 25; series 2 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Mt. Vernon II, 1991 March 19; series 2 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mt. Vernon College 4-17-98, 1998 April 06-17; series 2 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Poetry programs and notes, 1975-1984; series 2 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - St. Mary's, 1994; series 2 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - St. Mary's 80-87, 1980-1987; series 2 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - St. Mary's College conference, 1984-1986; series 2 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Strand interview, 1991; series 2 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Yardley article, 1987 May; series 2 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Capitol Hill Poetry Group files, 1977-2013; series 2
  This series contains correspondence, drafts of poetry written by Nordhaus and other Capital Hill Poetry Group members, as well as the group's manuscripts; book deal documents, the Capital Hill Poetry Group's bank account information, event information, and the Capital Hill Poetry Group's autobiographical organizational history, photos, and newspaper clippings featuring the group. There is also material related to Peter Petcoff that includes a cassette tape, event documents, and a tribute book of poetry. Materials range in date from 1977 to 2013, and represent the history of the Capital Hill Poetry Group in large part from the perspective of one of its co-founders, Jean Nordhaus.
  Capitol Hill Poetry Group
  - CH Poetry Group, 1995-2013; series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - CH Poetry Group - bank acct., 1992-1993; series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Corresp. with Wm. Meredith & his introduction to the book, 1979-1981; series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Friends' poems- poetry group [1/2], 1977-2013; series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Friends' poems-poetry group [2/2], 1977-2013; series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - GP manuscript, Circa 1979; series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Joel's poem about Shirley, me, us, Circa 1990; series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Other side II, 1995; series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Other side II - blurbs, old intro, 1996; series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    General
    Contains a photo
  - P/A Cap Hill Poetry Group old bank acct., 1984-1985; series 1 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Peter Petcoff-ceremony, poems, 1982; series 1 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Contains photos and a cassette tape
  - Poetry group - archives, 1979-1990; series 1 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Contains photos
  - Poetry group book, 1993; series 2 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Poetry group book-documents and correspondence, 1978-1982; series 2 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Poems for Peter with love from his poetic family, 1981; series 2 (Box 4, Folder 3)